בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is ס"ג *Samech Gimmel*, 63.
We're in the middle of the sixth פרק perek *perek*, האומר *Haomer*,
or sometimes called התקבל Itkabel *Hitkabel*, because that's the first... that's the
word after האומר *Haomer* and we're in the middle of a whole
discussion about whether when somebody says to a שליח shaliach *shaliach* of
the wife, הולך holech, גט get זה *holech get zeh*, convey this
גט get, *get* to my wife, whether הולך Holech. *holech* is כזכי
kezachi *k'zachi*, whether it really means to like take possession of it
now since anyway he's speaking to the person who is the שליח
shaliach *shaliach* of the wife and who can be receiving it right
now. So that's the question whether הולך Holech *holech* is כזכי ke-zachi
דמי *k'zachi dami* or not. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like
this: תא שמע ta shema, *Ta
shma*, come in here. I think that's where we left off. Three
lines on the wide lines of the... of ס"ו עמוד ב' *Samech
Vav amud bet*. We're a little bit behind. Okay, תא שמע ta
shema. *Ta shma*, come in here. לפיכך *Lefichach*, אם אמר לו הבעל
*im amar lo habaal*, if the בעל ba'al *baal* says to the
person who the wife appointed as a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabala. *shaliach
l'kabala*, a שליח shaliach *shaliach* to receive the גט get *get*, and
he said: אי אפשי ee efshi, שתקבל לה *Ee efshi shetikabel lah*,
it's... I don't want you to receive the גט get? *get* for
her. אלא *Ela* what I do want is הולך ותן לה Holech
VeTen Lah, *holech v'ten lah*, deliver it, convey it and give it
to her. So he's rejecting his role as a שליח לקבלה shaliach
lekabala. *shaliach l'kabala* and transferring him to a שליח להולכה shaliach leholacha.
*shaliach l'holacha*. So in that case, אם רצה לחזור יחזור im ratza
lachazor yachzor. *im ratza lachazor yachzor*. If he wants to, he can
retract before... before it gets to the wife because he's only a...
the גט get *get* has yet to be given because this שליח
shaliach *shaliach* is now serving as a שליח להולכה shaliach leholacha, *shaliach
l'holacha*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: טעמא דאמר אי אפשי ee
efshi *Ta'ama de'amar Ee efshi*. The reason that הולך holech *holech* there
means you're only to... we are four lines down in the wide
lines on ס"ו עמוד ב' *Samech Vav amud bet*. Okay? So the
reason that that הולך holech *holech* means you're going to convey the
גט get? *get* and be a שליח להולכה shaliach leholacha *shaliach l'holacha*
is because he explicitly said I do not want you to function
as a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabala. שתקבל לה *shaliach l'kabala shetikabel lah*.
אלא הולך ותן Holech VeTen. *Ela holech v'ten*. טעמא דאמר אי אפשי
*Ta'ama de'amar Ee efshi*, I'm sorry, we're five lines down. הא לא
אמר אי אפשי *Ha lo amar Ee efshi*, if he did not
say I don't want you, if he just said הולך holech, גט
get זה *holech get zeh* and he was speaking to a שליח
לקבלה shaliach lekabala. *shaliach l'kabala*, אם רצה לחזור לא יחזור im ratza
lachazor lo yachzor, *im ratza lachazor lo yachzor*. He can't retract. That
הולך holech *holech* would have been interpreted to mean receive this גט
get *get*. שמע מינה shema mina. הולך כזכי holech ke-zachi. דמי *Shma
mina holech k'zachi dami*. You see that the word הולך holech *holech*
means זכי Zechi, *zachi*, take possession. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says:
No, דילמא בהילך *dilma be'helach*. So that actually was a very good
proof because it was clear if he had just said הולך holech
*holech* it would have worked. He had to say I don't want
you to be a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabala, *shaliach l'kabala*, I want
you to convey it. So it sounds like הולך holech *holech* in
a normal context where he was a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabbala *shaliach
l'kabala* would have meant take the גט get *get* now, be the...
accept the גט get *get*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s basic only
response is to say maybe the word in the משנה mishna *Mishna*
is not הולך holech *holech* but הילך heilach *helach*. Now, to us
it sounds like okay, what's the difference, הולך holech, הילך heilach, *holech
helach*, sounds like the same word. But actually it's a completely different
word. הולך holech *holech* means הולכה Hoolacha *holacha*, to convey the גט
get *get*. הילך *He lach* means here is that which is yours.
You know, it's a completely different word. So basically it's saying if
he had just said הילך *he lach*, here it is, then... then
that would have been a... a giving of the גט get *get*.
Okay, so that's the case where it needs אי אפשי *Ee efshi*
to change the meaning of the word. But maybe הולך holech *holech*
by itself actually means to convey. Okay, so anyway, that's it's unclear,
is it switching the גירסא *girsa* of the משנה mishna, *Mishna*? What
is it doing? But anyway, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s a pretty good
evidence to the משנה mishna *Mishna* is that הולך holech *holech* would
have meant זכי zechi. *zachi*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying
well maybe the משנה mishna *Mishna* is talking about הילך *helach* and
not הולך holech, *holech*.
Yes, that's what he tells you today, but how is he able
to interfere with her agency?
Well, he's able to say I am refusing to give it to
you in the capacity as a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabbala. *shaliach l'kabala*.
So you can be a שליח לקבלה shaliach lekabbala, *shaliach l'kabala*, but
I'm not giving it to you for the purpose of you accepting
the גט get. *get* for your wife.
But that doesn't seem... I mean, I understand that, but it doesn't
seem like it should work.
Let's say you appointed somebody to buy my car from me, and
Michael to buy my car from me. And Michael came and said,
"So Dove, I want you to buy the car from..." He says,
"No, I refuse. I'm not going to sell the car to Dove
through you acting as Dove's agent. But what I will do is,
if you go and make a counteroffer to Dove and you want
to be my agent, I'll agree to that deal, right?"
But you also give him the key. What?
But you also give him the key.
Yeah, here's the key to the car, not for you to accept
it as Dove's agent, that I refuse to do, I refuse to
sell to Dove's agent. But I'll make you my agent and you
can give the key to Dove if you represent me and give
it to him, right?
Difference is that there's a two-way transaction, so Dove's not giving you
the money presumably. Right. If he gave you the $10,000... Right, and
you gave him the
key... Right...
then he wouldn't be acting on your behalf either.
Right, it's a one-sided transaction. I understand. So I mean it should
be more like... it seems to me it should be more... to
respect the agency of the other side.
I have no obligation to respect the agency of the other side.
But if you go ahead and give it... Right... you know, then...
then that should take control.
So you want to say that the very giving automatically plays into
the... into the pre-assigned...
Yeah, but okay, that's the חידוש *chidush* of the משנה mishna *Mishna*.
I mean, I'm still the one in charge and I'm refusing to...
Okay, so now the גמרא gmara continues. יומא ואילך. Yuma va'eylach.
So okay, so we haven't concluded with a הוליך holich is כזכי
ke-zachi, or not, and this is something that we will be revisiting.
So now the גמרא Gemara's says like this: פשיטא, pshita, איש הוי
שליח להולכה. ish havei shaliach leholacha.
Now we get into something that's a little bit easier to discuss
than just the question about the what exactly the language means, but
we'll be circling back. פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious that איש הוי שליח
להולכה, ish havei shaliach leholacha, that a man, a male can serve
as a שליח shaliach to deliver the גט get to the wife.
איש הוי שליח להולכה, ish havei shaliach leholacha,
שכן—I sheken lost my line—שכן בעל מוליך גט לאשתו, sheken baal molich
get leishto,
'cause men are the one who gives the גיטין gittin to their
wives. ואישה הוי שליח לקבלה, ve'ishah havei shaliach lekabalah, and it's obvious
that a woman could represent the wife to receive the גט, get.
שכן אישה מקבלת גיטה מיד בעלה, sheken ishah mekabelet gittah miyad baalah,
because women are the ones who receive the גיטין. gittin. But איש
לקבלה והאישה להולכה, ish lekabalah vehaishah leholacha,
thank you, can we have a man—just put it on the table—can
you have a man
who is assigned to receive a גט get? or can you have
a woman who is an agent to deliver a גט? get מאי?
mai? What's the story? I don't know, I mean, you're like the
same way we've learned before, you know, you can't make, let's say,
a non-Jew a שליח shaliach for something that they're not in the
פרשה. parsha. So are you enough that you're in the פרשה parsha
of גיטין gittin in general? Do you have to be in the
פרשה parsha of being the type of a person, you know, that
is in the פרשה parsha of receiving the גט get, or giving
the גט? get That's at least a הוה אמינא, hava amina, okay?
I agree with you. Why should we have an extra limitation and
restriction to those issues?
But they have to be married
in order to—well, right, I mean, so you could have maybe gone
that one step further if you had argued the first thing. But
anyway, the גמרא Gemara is going to reject it, but it least
wants to raise the question.
Okay. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. האומר התקבל גט זה
לאשתי haomer hitkabel get zeh leishti או הולך גט זה לאשתי, o
holich get zeh leishti, אם רצה לחזור יחזור. im ratza lachazor yachzor,
So a man, our משנה mishna. says, you know, bring this גט
get. to my wife, he can retract it. האישה שאמרה התקבל לי
גיטי, haishah she'amrah hitkabel li giti, if a woman says to somebody—we
don't know man or woman—receive my גט get. for me, אם רצה
לחזור לא יחזור, and the man gives it to that person, then
it's binding. מאי לאו בחד שליח? mai lav bechad shaliach? So presumably
the משנה, Mishnah the only thing it's changing is whether this guy
was appointed by the man or by the wife or the husband.
But it's
presumably talking about the same person being appointed. ושמע מינה כשר לקבלה
כשר להולכה. ushma mina kashar lekabalah kashar leholacha. So you see that
the same person who can serve as an agent for the man
can serve as an agent for the woman. So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא, בשני שלוחים. lo, bishnei sheluchim. Who said? Maybe the משנה
mishna. when it's talking about the man appointing an agent is talking
about a different agent than when the woman is appointing an agent?
And maybe it's talking about the man appointing a man and a
woman appointing a woman. Okay, תא שמע. Ta shma
Okay, that's a good question. Okay, תא שמע, Ta shema, it's a
good question. לפיכך אם אמר לו הבעל אי אפשי שתקבל לה אלא
הולך ותן לה. lefichach im amar lo habaal ee efshi shetikabel lah
ela holich veten lah. We have one case in the משנה mishna
where it's clear that the agent, as we've been talking about, switches
sides. He's a double agent, haha. Okay, לפיכך אם אמר לו הבעל
אי אפשי שתקבל לה אלא הולך ותן לה. lefichach im amar lo
habaal ee efshi shetikabel lah ela holich veten lah. If the husband
says to the wife's agent, "I refuse for you to accept the
גט get for her, but I will, but you can represent me
and go and deliver the גט get. for me," אם רצה לחזור
יחזור, Ratza lachazor yachazor. then he can retract because until the גט
get. is given.
והכא דחד שליח הוא, vehacha dechad shaliach hu, it's the same person.
ושמע מינה כשר לקבלה כשר להולכה. ushma mina kashar lekabalah kashar leholacha.
You see the person who represented the wife to receive the גט
get can now represent the husband to deliver the גט. get So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, פשט מינה, pashat minah, fine. You can
conclude from that definitely that one guy can—that somebody can operate as
both. But maybe only a man can operate as both and not
a woman. Why? Maybe we're talking about a man, and a man
can operate as both. Why would that be different? Because איש הוי
שליח לקבלה, ish havei shaliach lekabalah, maybe a man can receive a
גט get. for a wife, for a woman, שכן אב מקבל גט
לבתו קטנה, sheken av mekabel get levito ktanah, because we already have
a precedent of that, that a man receives a גט. get When
do we have a man receiving a גט? get, Because a father
of a minor daughter, the same way he marries off his minor
daughter, can receive a גט get for his minor daughter. So you're
right, the משנה mishna shows that one person can both be an
agent to give and receive a גט, get. but maybe that's a
man. Because maybe a man is in the פרשה parsha of receiving
a גט get, when a father receives for his daughter. Okay, but
maybe a woman cannot deliver a גט. get So let's take a
look. שכן אב מקבל גט לבתו קטנה. sheken av mekabel get levito
ktanah. אישה להולכה מיבעיא ליה, ishah leholacha mibaya lei, but I
still don't know whether a woman could be a שליח shaliach, to
deliver
a גט. get מאי? mai? What's the story? אמר רב מרי תא
שמע, amar Rav Mari ta shema, come and hear, we actually taught
this in an earlier משנה. mishna אף נשים שאינם נאמנות לומר מת
בעלה נאמנות להביא את גיטה, af nashim she'einam ne'emanot lomar met baalah
ne'emanot lehavi et gittah, women that are not believed to say that
a woman's husband died, like, you know, the mother-in-law and the sister-in-law
and all those women, right, that they're not believed as an עד
אחד ed echad to say that the husband died, because maybe they're
trying to mess her up, but they are believed to deliver a
גט get and to
say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. bifnai nichtav uvifnai nechtam. Okay, but what
did it have? It has women delivering a גט. get, Okay, so
there you go, it's a מפורש משנה. meforesh Mishnah. All
right. והתם הולכי v'hasam holochi and there's delivery of a גט. get
אלא רב אשי מסיפא נמי שמע מינה. Ella Rav Ashi miseifa nami
shema mina. You know it from the end of the משנה mishna
also clearly, דתני סיפא, de-tani seifa, האישה עצמה מביאה את גיטה ובלבד
שתהא צריכה לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. ha'ishah atzmah mevia et gitah
u-bilvad she-te'ei tzrichah lomar befanay nechtav u-befanay nechtam.
A woman could be her own שליח shaliach to deliver a גט
get to herself, which is bizarre, how do you be a שליח
shaliach. to deliver a גט get to yourself? Anyway, ואוקימנא בהולכה v'okimna
be'holachah and we said that that was talking about a woman being
a שליח shaliach to deliver a גט. get שמע מינה. It's actually
funny, you'd think the easier case was these other women being a
שליח, shaliach a woman being a שליח shaliach for herself is more
complicated. But anyway, be that as it may, okay, so now we've
at least clarified that for anybody, everybody here was saying what was
the הוה אמינא? hava amina? But you know what, just in case
anybody was going to ask, the גמרא Gemara's clarifies it black and
white that a man or a woman could play the role of
a שליח. shaliach
איתמר, itmar, it was taught: הבא לי גיטי, havei li giti, the
wife told her שליח shaliach התקבל לי גיטי. hitkabel li giti.
Now, here we're going to get into a whole series of interesting
cases where the שליח shaliach misreports to the husband his role. So
the woman tells the שליח shaliach receive my גט get for me.
הבא havei which means bring it, but it's understood to mean receive
my גט, get be my שליח לקבלה. shaliach lekabbala And the man
goes, I'm sorry, no, I misstated it, excuse me.
I misstated it, excuse me. The woman says הבא לי גיטי, havei
li giti, no as it does sound right that she says bring
it to me, meaning be a שליח shaliach for the husband. Okay,
actually it's a little bit confusing because you would think that the
only person that can make him a שליח shaliach's for the husband
is the husband. Okay, so it becomes an interesting question of do
you conceive of this concept called a שליח הולכה shaliach holachah that
the woman makes a שליח shaliach to bring the גט get, but
not to receive the גט. get. But we're going to just interpret
it that way.
No,
you can.
So what it means is, the way we're going to interpret it
means הבא לי גיטי havei li giti meaning I appoint, the woman,
the wife appoints somebody to say go to my husband and you
know, and present yourself and your services to be his שליח shaliach
to bring me my גט, get okay. But because it's confusing, it
raises a question of is there this concept called a שליח הולכה
shaliach holachah that the wife can create. But anyway, we're not going
to read it that way. Okay, so she tells the שליח shaliach's
go whatever, you know, go bring my גט get to me. And
now when he reports it to the husband, he says אשתך אמרה
התקבל לי גיטי. ishtecha amrah hitkabel li giti. Your wife wants me
to receive her גט get for her. He misrepresented, not intentionally necessarily,
but anyway, but he misrepresented himself to the husband, okay. Now, והוא
אומר vehu omer and then the husband says הילך כמה שאמרה. heilach
kemah she'amrah. Now here's הילך and הולך, holech. or here's הילך, here
it is like she said. Fine, take this גט get just as
my wife asked. Now, here's the question. What does he mean when
he says just as my wife asked? Just as you're reporting to
me that my wife asked? Or what I think my wife asked?
Okay, if it's what I, or no, excuse me, what you're reporting
to me, or what my wife actually asked? Okay, so אמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha amar Rav, אפילו הגיע גט לידה אינה מגורשת. afilu higia
get leyadah einah megureshet. Okay, even if he delivers the גט, get
it doesn't work. Why? Because he says that basically what I say
as my wife asked, what I mean is what you're telling me
my wife asked. So you're telling me my wife said give you
the גט get right now as
her שליח לקבלה. shaliach lekabbala. So I'm giving you the גט get
with my intent that it takes effect right now. I believe you're
the שליח לקבלה. shaliach le-kabala, But it doesn't take effect right now
because she never appointed this guy as a שליח לקבלה. shaliach le-kabala,
He's not in a position to represent the wife right now. So
fine, so then he takes the גט get and he gives it
to the wife, but then I the husband never appointed him as
my שליח
להולכה.
shaliach
leholacha,
So you wanted a divorce.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara is going to raise that possibility later. Do
we reinterpret what your דעת da'at is? But maybe we say no,
you said as my wife asked, which in this context means as
you're representing my wife's request. Since you aren't a שליח לקבלה, Shaliach
LeKabbalah. that doesn't work. Since I didn't make you a שליח להולכה,
shaliach leholacha that doesn't work. So it doesn't work.
So אפילו הגיע לידה אינה מגורשת. afilu higia leyadah einah megureshet. שמע
מינה אדיבורא דידיה קסמיך. shema mina adibura didey kasamich. We see that
the husband is relying on the שליח's shaliach report. And when he
says as my wife says it means as you are representing what
my wife says. דאי אדיבורא דידה קסמיך, de'i adibura didah kasamich, if
he meant what she actually said, he's relying on her statement, so
מטי גט לידה איגרשה. mati get leyadah itgarsah. So what she actually
said was you know, present, make yourself a שליח להולכה shaliach le'olacha.
for my husband. So when the husband says do what my wife
says, it means well, I don't know what my wife said, but
it turns out she wants you to be my שליח להולכה, shaliach
le'olacha. so I'm okay with that because I'm going along with what
she said, and you're my שליח להולכה shaliach le'olacha. and it should
work. Okay, so תתגרש, titgaresh, she should be divorced. So you see
that we don't say that. So according to this statement of רב
נחמן, Rav Nachman, of, excuse me, yeah, רב נחמן Rav Nachman in
the name of רבה בר אבוה Rabbah bar Avuha in the name
of רב, Rav, basically when there's a difference between what's being reported
and what she said and I say do what she said, I
mean as I am as you are representing what she said. אדיבורא
דידיה קסמיך. adibura didey kasamich. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, הכי
השתא. hachi hashta. How does this make any sense that that's how
what you conclude from that statement of רב נחמן Rav Nachman, *Rav
Nachman*? בשלמא איתמר *Bi'shlama i'itmar*. By the way, רב Rav אשי *Rav
Ashi* pointed out and what you have to be aware of is
that there's a סוגיא sugya *Sugia* in another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in
בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia* about this as a general question when the
שליח shaliach. *Shaliach* misrepresents what the משלח *Meshaleach* sent him for and
the other side says here, do this as that as your, as
the other side has said, do what does he mean? Do we
interpret it to mean as it was genuinely said or as you're
representing what he said? So this is by the way a general
question when this is misrepresented, right, whether we're assumed to work with
the original statement or the current statement. So now רב אשי *Rav
Ashi* says you cannot use this to conclude that other discussion. הכי
השתא Hechi hashta. *Hachi hasha*. What type of a comparison is this?
בשלמא איתמר איפכא *Bi'shlama i'itmar ipcha*.
If we had given the first case, התקבל לי גיטי hitkabel li
giti, *Hitkabel li giti*, that the wife says to the שליח shaliach
*Shaliach* receive the גט get *Get* for me. ושליחא אמרה *V'shlicha amra*,
and then he reports to the husband and he says, הוי לי
גיטי Hevi li giti *Havey li giti*. Your wife wants me to
deliver the גט get, *Get* to her. Okay to be your שליח
להולכה shaliach le'olacha. *Shaliach le'holacha*. והוא אמר Ve-hu amar, הילך כמה שאמרה
*V'hu amar haylach k'ma she'amra*, and the husband said here take it
like she said. In that case, now let's see what the consequence
would be. If it meant like you're representing what she said, so
you're saying be my שליח להולכה shaliach le-holacha, *Shaliach le'holacha*, right? Everybody
with me here? So okay, then I am genuinely making him a
שליח להולכה shaliach le-holacha. *Shaliach le'holacha* and when it gets delivered she
should be מגורשת *Megureshet*. Okay. If I meant what she said what
she really said, and then she would be divorced from then your
שליח לקבלה Shaliach LeKabbalah. *Shaliach le'kabala* and she'd be divorced from the
minute the גט get *Get* got to his hand. Okay. So that
case, if it goes by, maybe I need to start
diagramming. Okay, that's okay. Anyway, so she says, here here's the wife,
and she says in this case okay התקבל Itkabel,
*Hitkabel*.
Okay just like קבלה kabala *Kabala*. He makes her a שליח לקבלה
Shaliach LeKabbalah, *Shaliach le'kabala*. He goes and he says to the husband
I'm a שליח להולכה shaliach le-holacha *Shaliach le'holacha*. Okay and then this
guy what what will make him a husband I don't know we'll
give him a beard or something I don't know that makes him
a husband. Anyway he says כמה שאמרה *K'ma she'amra*. Okay. So in
this case if you go by what he thinks she's saying הולכה
Hoolacha *Holacha* then he can genuinely make him a שליח להולכה shaliach
le-holacha *Shaliach le'holacha*. He's in a power to make him a שליח
להולכה Shaliach LeHoolacha. *Shaliach le'holacha* and then when he gives it there
she would be מגורשת *Megureshet*. Okay right so she'd be מגורשת *Megureshet*
here right
if he meant like this. If he meant כמה שאמרה *K'ma she'amra*
if it goes like what קבלה kabala, *Kabala* then if it goes
then she'd be divorced I don't know how to diagram this. Anyway
okay if however it means קבלה Kabbalah *Kabala* thinks she's מגורשת *Megureshet*
right away. All right. So then the difference between between which one
does she mean would determine whether it's only when it gets here
or when it's immediately. Let's read that. Okay. התקבל hitkabel לי גיטי
ושליחא אמרה הוי לי גיטי והוא אמר הילך כמה שאמרה *Hitkabel li
giti v'shlicha amra havey li giti v'hu amar haylach k'ma she'amra*. אמר
רב amar Rav, נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב amar Rav,
*Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha amar Rav*: כיון שהגיע לידו
מגורשת *Kivan she'higia le'yado megureshet*. It would happen right away. אלמא דיבור
דידה הוא דקסמיך *Alma dibur dida hu d'kasamikh*. Then we would know
that she's he means what she actually said. אינמי *Inami* or
if he said לידה *Le'yada* that she's divorced when she gets it,
not when the שליח shaliach, *Shaliach* gets it. אדיבורא דידיה קסמיך *Adibur
diday kasamikh* he's going by what the שליח shaliach. *Shaliach* said and
he's making him into a שליח להולכה Shaliach LeHoolacha. *Shaliach le'holacha*. אלא
הכא *Ela hacha* but but this case is the reverse. Okay משום
דעקר שליח shaliach לשליחותיה לגמרי הוא דאמר *Mishum de'akar shaliach l'shlichutay le'gamray
hu de'amar*. דאמר שליח לקבלה הוינא De'amar shaliach lekabbala havina, להולכה לא
הוינא *De'amar shaliach le'kabala havina le'holacha lo havina*. Here the reason it
doesn't work now here if the case is the reverse right here's
the case is
she says הולכה Hoolacha. *Holacha* and he says קבלה Kabbalah, *Kabala*. So
and we're saying that it doesn't work. Okay so we're saying it
doesn't work. So why doesn't it work? Well if if we're saying
well if he was going by what the wife said קבלה Kabbalah.
*Kabala* excuse me all right הולכה *Holacha*. If it was going by
what the שליח shaliach *Shaliach* said קבלה Kabbalah, *Kabala* then we understand
it doesn't work. He wanted it to work right away but she
had never appointed him a שליח לקבלה Shaliach LeKabbalah. *Shaliach le'kabala*. If
it was going by what she said הולכה *Holacha* then it should
have worked. He appointed him a שליח להולכה Shaliach LeHoolacha. *Shaliach le'holacha*
and he got delivered. Okay so the fact that we're saying it
doesn't work shows you're going by what the שליח shaliach *Shaliach* said.
That was the proof. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no not
necessarily because when this guy is saying your wife says שליח לקבלה
Shaliach LeKabbalah. *Shaliach le'kabala* forget what the husband has in mind. The
wife appointed him with the with the responsibility of bringing the גט
get *Get* back to to her or at least said I'll have
you represent my husband and bring the גט get *Get* back to
me. When he says I'm going to be I'm a שליח לקבלה
Shaliach LeKabbalah *Shaliach le'kabala* he's making his life a lot easier right
because if he's a שליח לקבלה Shaliach LeKabbalah. *Shaliach le'kabala* the job
is done as soon as he receives the גט get, *Get*. Everybody
get that point? Okay so what we're saying is the reason it
doesn't work here is not a function of is he going by
what her the husband going by what she said or by what
he said. The reason it doesn't work is we assume to interpret
the שליח shaliach. *Shaliach* saying I'm a שליח לקבלה Shaliach LeKabbalah, *Shaliach
le'kabala* as rejecting the role of being the שליח shaliach, *Shaliach* to
bring the גט get *Get* back to the wife. She wants me
to bring it back to her? No I refuse that. I'm only
going to be The reason it doesn't work is we interpret the
שליח shaliach. saying I'm a שליח לקבלה shaliach le-kabala. as rejecting the
role of being the שליח shaliach. to bring the גט get. back
to the wife. He wants me to bring it back to her?
No, I refuse that. I'm only going to be prepared to be
a שליח לקבלה. shaliach le-kabala, And that's why it doesn't work, because
the שליח shaliach is refusing to play the other role, okay? So
that's the reason. It has nothing to do with what the husband
said. So let's read that.
השתא אבל הכא משום דאקרי שליח לשליחותיה לגמרי הוא. Hashta aval hacha
mishum de'akrei shaliach lishlichutei legamrei hu. It's because he's rejecting the שליחות.
shlichut. דאמר שליח לקבלה shaliach le-kabala, הוינא, I am prepared to be
a שליח לקבלה, shaliach l'kabala ולאולוכא לא הוינא, ulo'ulacha lo havina, I
won't be a שליח להולכה. Shaliach LeHoolacha. And he can't be a
שליח לקבלה shaliach l'kabala, because she never appointed him a שליח לקבלה.
shaliach le-kabalah. All right? So just from the statement of רבה בר
אבא Rabba bar Abba of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman. we don't know
whether it's דיבורא דידה dibbura didah or דיבורא דידיה. dibbura didei. His
פסק psak might be based on the interpreting the שליח's shaliach word
as a rejection of the role that the wife is okay with.
Wait, you know we have on the other hand we have sometimes
עיגונא גילוי בדרבנן. iguna gilui bederabbanan. So you know she clearly wants
to be
divorced.
Okay, we're going to get to that, okay? We're going to get
to those possibilities. But you also still have to play by the
rules. So when are we prepared to reinterpret or not? Okay, so
we have this as an open question. Yes?
The שליח shaliach, was assigned from the court or the No,
no, an agent of the person, not of the court.
Anyone can go?
Yep, anyone can make a שליח. shaliach, Yep. So which makes things
a little confusing. Okay, so now we have this as an open
question. We have this concept that we can interpret the words of
a שליח shaliach when he's making his life easier as rejecting the
role that he was assigned. But besides which we have this open
question when the husband says, "Like she said," which what does he
mean? "Like she really said," or "Like I understand what she said"?
So let's take a look. אמר רב הונא בר חייא תא שמע.
Amar Rav Huna bar Chiya ta shma. So we're going to bracket
this reinterpretation of rejecting the role and go back to this question
of which "like she said" do we mean? תא שמע come and
hear. האומר התקבל גט זה לאשתי Ha'omer hitkabel get zeh le'ishti או
הולך גט זה לאשתי. o holech get zeh le'ishti. So a man
says, "Receive this גט get, for my wife"
or "convey it to her," and obviously it really only means convey
it to her because that's the only thing he can say. רצה
לחזור יחזור. Ratza Lehachazir Yachazir. He can retract. טעמא דרצה הא לא
רצה הוי גט. Ta'ama deratza ha lo ratza havei get. So the
only reason
he can
retract, meaning if he wants to, he can retract. But if he
doesn't want to, meaning if he lets the גט get be delivered,
it's obviously a גט, get which is obvious. Okay, so what's the
problem? It's a גט. get ואמאי הבעל לאו בר שויי שליח לקבלה
הוא? Ve'amai habaal lav bar shavei shaliach lekabbala hu?
So one minute, meaning he's going back to the obvious case in
the משנה. mishna, The משנה mishna, doesn't make any sense. The משנה
Mishna. says if a husband says to the שליח, shaliach, "Accept this
גט get. for my wife," right, that it works when the גט
get, is delivered. We interpret those words as making him a שליח
להולכה. Shaliach LeHoolacha. But why? He said, "Accept this גט get. for
my wife." The literal meaning, meaning this is exactly, Michael, your point.
If we're going to be overly literal, then we're ignoring what it's
clear he wants to do. And I'll show you in the משנה
Mishna we interpret his words based on what we know he wants
to do. Because the משנה Mishna. says if I say to Michael,
"Michael, accept this גט get, for my wife," then I'm making Michael
a שליח להולכה. Shaliach LeHoolacha Now, how is that true? I never
said deliver it to my wife. I said accept it for her,
which means he would represent my wife. But obviously he can't represent
my wife; she didn't make him a שליח. shaliach So even though
I said receive it for her, we interpret those words to mean
deliver it to her. So we're not going to be overly literal;
we're going to go by context. Okay, exactly your question, Michael. ואמאי
הבעל לאו בר שויי שליח לקבלה הוא? Ve'amai habaal lav bar shavei
shaliach lekabbala hu? I can't make Michael a שליח Shaliach. to accept
the גט Get for my wife. So when I say, "Accept this
גט Get for my wife," I mean I'm going to interpret it
in the way that is the only thing that can make sense
in this context, something that can allow the גט Get. to be
given, which means deliver it to her wife. אלא אמרינן, Ella amrinan,
we say, כיון שנתן עיניו לגרשה, keivan shenatan einav le'garsha, since it's
clear I'm trying to divorce her, מימר אמר תיגרש בכל היכי דמגרשה.
meimar amar tigaraish bechol heichi demigaraisha. I say, no, you know what
I mean, whatever it's going to take for me to say to
make him deliver the גט get, to my wife, that's what I
mean. So we interpret the words based on what clearly he's trying
to accomplish.
Okay. הכא נמי כיון שנתן עיניו לגרשה מימר אמר תיגרש בכל היכי
דמגרשה. Hacha nami keivan shenatan einav le'garsha meimar amar tigaraish bechol heichi
demigaraisha. So here too, we should say in this case, let's ignore
the idea that we're going to say that the שליח Shaliach is
rejecting his role. In this case where he says he's לקבלה, lekabbala,
but he wasn't appointed לקבלה, lekabbala, we'll interpret what the husband wants
him to do is take the גט get. in any way that's
going to work, and in this capacity the only way it's going
to work is if he's a שליח להולכה. shaliach le-holacha, Okay, so
come on, let's give it a little latitude. Okay. הכי
השתא. hachi hasht, What type of comparison is that?
התם איהו ידע דאין שליחות לקבלה לגביה ונחתי לשם הולכה. Hatam ihu
yada de'ein shlichut lekabbala gabeih venachtei leshem holacha. There we can say
that, you
know, it's there's no possible genuine mistake the person is making. Like
the person, or here he's like saying
clearly what he wanted to say was deliver the גט, get because
he knows that I can't appoint the שליח Shaliach for לקבלה lekabbala
for my wife. Okay, now I don't know if we really know
that; why do we assume that people know the הלכה? halacha? Okay,
I don't know. But anyway, but the point is... Assuming you do
know the הלכה, halakha, okay, we'll say that, you know, anybody who
knew the הלכה halakha would have known that the only thing that
could be said here is deliver a גט get, for my wife
in the case in the משנה, Mishna not receive it. So we're
going to interpret receive it to mean deliver it. Okay, but הכא
טעי, hacha ta'i, but in this case, he genuinely thinks this guy
is a שליח Shaliach לקבלה, right? So he genuinely wants this to
be a קבלה Kabbalah and that would have been a case maybe
this helps you to understand it, that would have been a case
that according to his דעת da'at it would have worked. So when
according to his own דעת da'at it would have worked, we're not
going to interpret it in a different way that it'll work based
on the actual facts of the case. But when he says to
a normal guy, accept the גט get for my wife, according to
his דעת da'at it wouldn't have worked, right? Because he because he
because he thinks
let's say he doesn't know the הלכה, halakha, he thinks he can
make this guy a שליח Shaliach לקבלה, he can't, okay, so according
to his own דעת, da'at, you know, according to what he's trying
to do it wouldn't have worked, we're going to interpret it in
a way that it could have. But here, he's mistaken about the
facts, but according to his understanding of the facts it really would
have worked, so he really wants it to work this way. So
therefore it doesn't work. We're not going to reinterpret what he's saying,
right? Okay, what?
It's kind of ironic.
I understand, I mean, the point is not like על פי הלכה
al pi halakha the point is that it's not על פי הלכה
al pi halakha we want the גט get to work. The point
is, we have to be able to argue that even though a
person said X, he really meant Y. Okay, so in the case
of the משנה, Mishna he said X, but anybody who knew the
הלכה halakha would have known that X doesn't work. So we're going
to interpret what he really means to say is Y. Whereas in
this case, we can't say what he really meant to say was
something else, because because because had the facts been as he assumed
it, that statement would have worked. So we can't just reinterpret and
say oh, had he not been mistaken about the facts. But he
was mistaken about the facts.
This still seems like, you know, looking at the trees and, you
know, it's at the expense of the forest.
I understand. Anyway, the point is, we're not going to just arbitrarily
interpret what he says in to be a way that it works.
We have to say deep down this is what he really meant
to say. We can't say he really meant to say something when
he was mistaken about the facts and he really did mean to
say what he did say based on his misunderstanding of the facts.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבא תא שמע,
Amar Rava ta shema, come in here. קטנה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי
אינו גט עד שיגיע גט לידה,
Ketana she-amra hitkabel li
giti eino get ad she-yagi'a get le-yada, a minor woman, girl, cannot
make a שליח. Shaliach's So if she says to somebody, bring me
my גט, get it's not a גט get until she gets the
גט. get Okay. He can be someone's שליח, Shaliach, just not for
like not just not a קבלה, Kabbalah. right? No. This is a
five year old. No שליחות shlichus at all, right? The husband makes
him into a שליח. Shaliach She can't make him into a שליח.
Shaliach's She says to somebody, be my שליח shaliach. to accept the
גט, get so and the guy goes to the husband and says,
you know, your your underage wife made me a שליח shaliach, to
accept the גט get and I give the גט get. to him.
So in that case, it's a גט get when it gets delivered
to her because
then I've made him a שליח, shaliach okay, but she hasn't made
him a שליח, shaliach she's a minor. Okay. אינו גט עד שיגיע
גט לידה.
Eino get ad
she-yagi'a get le-yada.
כי מטו גט לידה
מי מיגרשה?
Ki matu get
le-yada mi megarsha?
But when she gets it is she divorced? אמר אביי והא שליח
להולכה שוייה, Amar Abaye ve-ha shaliach le-holacha shavye, but when I gave
it to this guy, this guy said oh, I'm a שליח shaliach
of your underage wife to accept the גט. get So I never
said he was to be a שליח להולכה, shaliach l'holacha? I just
gave it to him. אלא אמינא כיון דנתן מאמן לגרשה מימר מיגרש
כהיכא דמיגרשה. Ela amina kevan de-natan me-aman le-gareshah mimar me-garesh kahach de-megarsha.
So, but what we do is we say no, but clearly you
want to divorce your wife, so we'll interpret it that by giving
to him you are making him into a שליח להולכה. shaliach l'holacha,
So you see we reinterpret it even though I didn't make him
a שליח להולכה shaliach le-holacha we say I did. Somebody says no,
הכי השתא, Hachi Hashata, same point. התם איהו ידע דאין שליחות לקטן,
Hatam ihu yada de-ein shlichus le-katan, or you should know that there's
no שליחות shlichus for קטן. katan. So there, right, when you are
making a mistake in the law we basically say, basically the difference
is a mistake in the law is a mistake in the fact,
okay. Either because you're making a mistake in the law we're going
to say people really do or should know the law, so deep
down you want to do it in the legal way in which
it's really going to work. So even if you're not an expert
in the law, you would want to conform to the legal requirements
to make it work. So if so if you know or because
you should know whatever there's no שליחות shlichus for קטן, katan, we
say גמר ונתן לשום הלכה, gamar ve-nasah lishum halakha, when you gave
it to your minor wife's שליח, shaliach you really were implicitly making
a שליח shaliach להולכה because because there that was the legal way
that such a transaction could work. להלכתא דידיה, Le-halakhta dideh, his own.
הכא
טעי, Hacha ta'i,
but here the problem is not a mistake in the law, the
problem is a mistake in the fact. And therefore we're going to
say you thought given those facts that it was going to work,
we're not going to interpret it in a way based on a
different understanding of the facts. תא שמע, come in here. הוי לי
גיטי and אשתך אמרה התקבל לי
גיטי. ishtecha amra hitkabel li giti. Now the שליח shaliach says to
the wife says bring me my גט, get and then he reports
it as your wife said to me accept my גט. get Or
התקבל לי גיטי, or the wife said accept my גט, get and
he reports אשתך אמרה הוי לי גיטי, ishtecha amra hevi li giti,
okay, and receive it. והוא אמר, now what did the husband say?
As opposed to the before... Or the husband says, here do as
she says. Here is what he said: הולך ותן לה, Holech VeTen
Lah זכי לה, Zechi Lah, והתקבל לה. VeItkabel Lah. Okay, so it
is getting very confusing. Okay, we have two scenarios and the husband
saying four things which we're going to break into two. Okay, הולך
ותן לה holech ve-ten la. is one thing, deliver it to her.
זכי והתקבלי לה Zechi VeItkabeli Lah is another thing, receive it. רצה
לחזור יחזור. Then he can retract. משיגיע גט לידה מגורשת. MisheYagiya Get
LeYadah Megureshet. But once she gets the hand, the get, she's divorced.
Meaning he's a שליח shaliach. להולכה. Now מאי לאו קבלה אקבלה והולכה
אהולכה? Mai Lav Kabbalah A'Kabbalah VeHoolacha A'Hoolacha? So here what we're going
to do is we gave two scenarios. One where she said be
a שליח הולכה Shaliach Hoolacha and he said I'm a שליח קבלה.
Shaliach Kabbalah. The other scenario is she said be a שליח קבלה
Shaliach Kabbalah and he said I'm a שליח הולכה. Shaliach Hoolacha. And
then the, what does the husband say? So it gives us what
the husband said, two types of responses. One is זכי, zichi right?
הולך holech ותן.
And the other is זכי והתקבלי, Zechi VeItkabeli,
right? Or והתקבל, VeItkabel, התקבלי. Itkabeli. Okay, so we are going to
assume, which is a pretty good read of the ברייתא, Braita, that
the husband is responding based on what he hears from the שליח.
shaliach So the שליח shaliach says I'm a שליח shaliach. לקבלה. He
says fine, receive it. The שליח shaliach says I'm a שליח shaliach
להולכה. He says fine, deliver it. Of course, what else is the
husband going to say? He's going to say based on what he
understands. And what does it say? It says in all these cases
it's a גט get when she receives it. Okay, so let's figure
this out. In this case, he says I'm a שליח shaliach, להולכה.
He makes him a שליח shaliach, להולכה. So of course, it doesn't
matter that the wife made him a שליח shaliach, לקבלה. The husband
is not giving it to him for קבלה Kabbalah purposes, giving it
to him for הולכה purposes. He's a שליח shaliach להולכה.
And this contradicts our משנה. mishnah Why? Because the משנה says that
the שליח shaliach was מעכב Me'akev the שליחות, Shlichut, his שליחות. Shlichut.
Oh no, not our משנה. The גמרא's Gemara reinterpretation of רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman But okay, let's just work with this. Okay, so this
case makes total sense. He appointed him a שליח shaliach, להולכה and
he did not give it to him for קבלת הגט. Kabbalat HaGet.
So it's a גט get when he delivers it. This case, he
wants him to be a שליח shaliach לקבלה, right? That's in his
mind, he wants him to be a שליח shaliach, לקבלה. He was
not appointed as a שליח shaliach, לקבלה. So
then it shouldn't be good even when he gives it to her.
So you see that רב נחמן Rav Nachman, is wrong, that in
that case A, he's not עוקר Oker his שליחות, Shlichut, right? He's
not refusing. And that we interpret that even though he's saying accept
it for him, which we're really going to interpret in a way,
whatever way it's going to work, okay? So it's a complete contradiction
of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman. right? Because this case is even explicit
that he thinks he's a שליח shaliach לקבלה and it's going to
work when he delivers the גט. get So the גמרא Gemara, says,
isn't that what we're talking about?
Where were we?
Hold on. Okay. מאי לאו קבלה אקבלה והולכה אהולכה לא קבלה אהולכה
והולכה אקבלה. Mai Lav Kabbalah A'Kabbalah VeHoolacha A'Hoolacha? Lo, Kabbalah A'Hoolacha VeHoolacha
A'Kabbalah. So now it's going to say, no, no, no. The משנה
is not that way. I don't know why we would assume this.
Maybe because the משנה wants to complicate things. So say she says
A, he says B, and he goes back and says A. Okay,
so we're going to read this ברייתא Braita as, you know, here
he says התקבל and here he says הולך. holech Okay, that's the
case. Now will that work? Let's figure this out. So in this
case, he says I'm a קבלה, he says no, I want you
to be a שליח הולכה. Shaliach Hoolacha. That'll work when she gets
it. But in this case, she made the שליח shaliach? לקבלה. He
gave it to him as קבלה. She should be divorced right away.
So that doesn't explain it. Okay, let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא קבלה אהולכה והולכה אקבלה אי קבלה אהולכה מכדי
מטא גיטא לידיה לאלתר להווי גיטא. Lo, Kabbalah A'Hoolacha VeHoolacha A'Kabbalah. I
Kabbalah A'Hoolacha Michdi Mata Gitta LeYadeih L'altar LeHevei Gitta. No, then over
here she should be divorced right away. שמע מינה דדיבורא דידיה קסמיך.
Shma Mina DeDibbura Dideih KaSamich. So what you see is even in
this case, if you're going to read the ברייתא Braita your way,
it still proves it our way. Because even when he says הולכה
and he says קבלה, קבלה doesn't mean קבלה. קבלה means, like really
like you said, הולכה. So even when he explicitly says something else,
we're going to interpret it in light of what the שליח shaliach
said. So certainly if he just says like, do what she said,
right? We're going to reframe his statement based on the שליח's shaliach
statement.
Yeah, but in the second case, if it was just if he
סמיך Samich on the שליח, shaliach. then it should be right away.
No, because she never appointed him שליח shaliach לקבלה, so it can't
function that way. Okay, but then of course then you should say
then it shouldn't work at all. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. So you see, nevertheless you see שמע מינה דדיבורא דידיה
קסמיך. Shma Mina DeDibbura Dideih KaSamich. הכי השתא, what type of comparison
is that? התם קאמר ליה הולך כמה שאמרה הכא מי קאמר הילך
כמה שאמרה? Hatam Ka'amar Lei Holech Kema She'amrah, Hacha Mi Ka'amar Heilech
Kema She'amrah? The גמרא's Gemara going to say, no, this case is
better. Because in this case, okay, if she's just saying, he says
הולך holech and he says התקבל, we're prepared to say whatever you
said is interpreted in light of what the שליח shaliach said. And
you really made a שליח הולכה, Shaliach Hoolacha, which is bizarre. Why
should we allow the שליח's shaliach words to more define what the
husband is doing than what the husband himself said? But maybe you're
right, in this case we'll define it as a שליח הולכה. Shaliach
Hoolacha. But... If instead of saying התקבל he said כמה שאמרה היא,
kema she-amra hee,
he made it based on what she had said, okay, and she
had said in that case something else, so maybe it's not defined
by the שליח. shaliach If he says something opposite the שליח, shaliach
we'll say the שליח shaliach frames what he means. But if he's
basically giving the right to define the שליח's shaliach role based on
the wife's role, then in that case maybe, right, it totally goes
by what the wife said. So that is again, it's a little
complicated, but the גמרא's Gemara right trying to say every case you
have that seems to say we're going to frame it in a
way that works, maybe it's not true. Maybe when he says כמה
שאמרה היא kema she-amra hee ultimately it goes by what the wife
originally intended, okay, or different than what is being said right now.
So the גמרא Gemara says okay,
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So we don't really resolve that case, although
again the simple evidence of that is like you guys were saying,
is that like we are prepared if it's not going to work
the way he said it, we're going to be prepared to interpret
it in a way that will work. But the גמרא's going... it
says not necessarily every case would we say that. Okay.
What? Yeah, so we haven't directly disproven רב נחמן. We're trying to
argue against him, but we haven't like directly disproven him. Okay. All
right. So now the גמרא says like this. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan.
התקבלי גיטי ואשתך אמרה התקבלי גיטי והוא אמר הולך ותן לה זכי
לה והתקבלה רצה להחזיר לא יחזיר.
hitkabli gitti ve-ishtecha amra hitkabli gitti ve-hu
amar holech ve-ten la zechi la ve-hitkablah ratza lehachzir lo yachzir. Okay,
so
here's a simple case, simple, haha. Now we're so glad to get
back to our משנה the case. Okay. He's reporting directly. He's a
שליח shaliach לקבלה. But the husband says to the שליח shaliach לקבלה,
הולך ותן לה. holech ve-ten la Okay, so that's that's the question
whether הולך holech, is כזכי ke-zachi or not. He says הולך ותן
לה holech ve-ten la. which could mean either here, take it and
and accept it for her, but the simple sense of the words
is deliver it to her. And then the other cases are easier.
זכי לה והתקבלה. zechi la ve-hitkablah. Okay. רצה להחזיר לא יחזיר. ratza
lehachzir lo yachzir. So according to the תנא קמא tanna kamma either
way it's binding immediately. So the question we raised at the beginning
of the פרק whether הולך holech is כזכי, ke-zachi, this ברייתא braita
is explicit. The guy comes and he reports and he says I'm
your wife's שליח shaliach to receive the גט, get and he says
הולך, holech, and we say it's binding right away. Okay. So that's
הולך כזכי. holech ke-zachi, The question we raised earlier is resolved here.
Okay. רבי אומר לא יחזיר. Rabbi omer lo yachzir. רבי נתן אומר
הולך ותן לה רצה להחזיר יחזיר. Rabbi Natan omer holech ve-ten la
ratza lehachzir yachzir. No,
when he says הולך holech even though the guy is a שליח
shaliach. לקבלה, okay, it is not binding right away, and he can
retract it until the wife gets the גט. get זכי לה והתקבלה
רצה להחזיר לא יחזיר. zechi la ve-hitkablah ratza lehachzir lo yachzir. Okay.
However, when he says accept it for her, then it is binding.
So this exact question is הולך כזכי, holech ke-zachi right, it's so
funny that we raised it before and here it's an explicit debate
of the תנא קמא tanna kamma and רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. רבי
אומר בכולן אם רצה להחזיר לא יחזיר. Rabbi omer be-chulan im ratza
lehachzir lo yachzir.
He can't retract, which is the same position of the תנא קמא,
tanna kamma, right, הולך also means זכי. zichi, אבל אם אמר לו
אי אפשי שתקבל לה אלא הולך ותן לה. aval im amar lo
ee efshi she-tikabel lah ela holech ve-ten la. I refuse, you know,
I don't want you to receive it for her, but הולך ותן
לה. If he starts with the אי אפשי, then הולך means deliver.
Then רצה להחזיר יחזיר. ratza lehachzir yachzir. Okay, which is exactly the
position of the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, which is הולך is כזכי
k'zichi unless you say I refuse. גמרא says רבי היינו תנא קמא,
Rabbi hainu tanna kamma, isn't that the תנא קמא? tanna kamma?
אי בעית אימא
אי אפשי אתא לאשמועינן,
ee
ba'it eima
ee efshi ata le-ashmueinan, he's clarifying that when you start by saying
אי אפשי then הולך does mean הולך, does mean deliver. ואי בעית
אימא הא קמשמע לן מאן תנא קמא רבי, ve-ee ba'it eima ha
kamashma lan man tanna kamma Rabbi, he's just clarifying that that's רבי's
Rabbi position. Okay. So anyway the question we raised earlier is הולך
כזכי holech ke-zachi. is a debate of תנא קמא tanna kamma slash
רבי Rabbi versus
רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. That רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, what true, רבי
נתן, Rabbi Natan, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says הולך is לאו כזכי,
lav ke-zachi, even in the context where the שליח shaliach says, and
this gets back to this question also, right, because as I said
yesterday there are two contexts of הולך כזכי. holech ke-zachi One is
no context, like I take a guy and I say Michael, I
want to I want to free my slave, הולך ושחרר לו holech
ve-shichrer lo to my slave. So there, I'm working on a blank
slate. So there it's more likely to say הולך means deliver, not
be זוכה zocheh for, for my slave, right, and it could mean
זוכה zocheh because it's a זכות zechut for my slave to be
free, but it's a blank slate so הולך in a blank context
should mean deliver, not not receive it for him. But then if
Michael comes and says I'm your wife's שליח shaliach to receive her
גט get. and I say הולך, so already we're predisposed to interpret
that as that this will be the binding transaction right here, right?
So that context to say הולך כזכי holech k'zichi, makes a lot
more sense. Is that clear? Because you know, you're already saying like
your wife wants me to receive her גט, get fine, הולך. Okay,
so there we might just frame it based on, you know, the
way Michael the שליח shaliach. and the wife have already framed the
transaction. So in that position the תנא קמא tanna kamma and רבי
Rabbi says הולך is כזכי, k'zichi, and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says
no, even there, הולך goes by the simple meaning of the words
and he's only making him שליח shaliach להולכה, not a
שליח. shaliach. We raised the question: היליך *heilech* רבי
נתן Rabbi Natan *Rabbi Natan* כזכי k'zichi? דמי או לאו כזכי דמי
*k'zachi dami o lav k'zachi dami*? So הולך *holech* doesn't mean זכי
zichi *zachi*, but היליך *heilech*, היליך *heilech* should totally mean כזכי *k'zachi*
because היליך *heilech* means הי לך *hei lach*, here it is, take
it. Okay, so היליך *heilech*, does that for רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan*
mean זכי zichi, *zachi*? Logically it totally other than the fact that
it sounds like הולך *holech*, like logically it totally should, right? So
let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. תא שמע *ta shema*, come
and hear. האומר התקבל גט get זה לאשתי או הולך גט get
זה לאשתי רצה לחזור יחזור *ha'omer hitkabel get ze l'ishti o holech
get ze l'ishti ratza lachzor yachzor*. Okay, if you say התקבל *hitkabel*
or הולך *holech* you can retract. האשה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי רצה
לחזור לא יחזור *ha'isha she'amra hitkabel li giti ratza lachzor lo yachzor*.
But when a woman makes her שליח shaliach לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah* she
can't retract as soon as the guy gets the גט get *get*
because it's binding. מאי לאו *mai lav* בהיליך ורבי נתן *b'heilech v'Rabbi
Natan*?
Okay, and now one minute, one minute, oh, since it says התקבל
או הולך גט זה לאשתי *hitkabel o holech get ze l'ishti*, so
for some reason we are assuming that the הולך *holech* really here
means היליך *heilech* and it's רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan*. It's a very
bizarre assumption. Maybe we just want it to go לדברי הכל *l'divrei
hakol*. Okay, so מאי לאו *mai lav*, don't we say that, I
mean this is just our משנה *mishna*. האשה שאמרה התקבל לי *ha'isha
she'amra hitkabel li*, right? האומר התקבל או הולך *ha'omer hitkabel o holech*.
So shouldn't we say that this is a case of היליך ורבי
נתן *heilech v'Rabbi Natan*? Wait, wait, oh no no no, I'm sorry,
I misinterpreted. When it says האשה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי רצה לחזור
לא יחזור *ha'isha she'amra hitkabel li giti ratza lachzor lo yachzor* means
this case, excuse me, that's why. This case that the husband said
הולך *holech* or התקבל *hitkabel*, if the wife had already said to
the guy "be my שליח shaliach. לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah*", then it's binding.
Okay, you got the case? Meaning it says if a guy if
the husband says to the שליח shaliach *shaliach*, הולך *holech* or התקבל
גט זה לאשתי *hitkabel get ze l'ishti*, he's a שליח shaliach להולכה
*shaliach l'holacha*. However, says the ברייתא *braita*, if the wife had already
made this guy a שליח shaliach. לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah* and the husband
says הולך *holech* or התקבל *hitkabel*, then it's binding right away. So
you see that the הולך *holech* of the husband when the guy's
a שליח shaliach לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah* means that it's binding. So aren't
we so let's say that this is everyone, לדברי הכל *l'divrei hakol*.
מאי לאו בהיליך *mai lav b'heilech*? Let's say it's a case that
he didn't say הולך *holech*, he said היליך *heilech* and it's לדברי
הכל *l'divrei hakol*. So if the guy's a שליח shaliach. לקבלה *shaliach
l'kabbalah* and the husband says היליך *heilech*, it's binding. רבי נתן *Rabbi
Natan*, לא בהולך ורבי *lo b'holech v'Rebbi*. No, why should we say
that? It's a case of הולך *holech*. If the guy's a שליח
shaliach לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah* and this is following רבי *Rebbi* that הולך
*holech* is כזכי *k'zachi*. Okay, תא שמע *ta shema*, come and hear.
לפיכך אם אמר לו הבעל אי אפשי שתקבל לו *lefikach im amar
lo haba'al ee efshi shetikabel lo* the husband says, right? I don't
want, this is our משנה *mishna*. I don't want you to to
be her שליח shaliach לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah*. אלא הולך ותן לה *ela
holech v'ten lah*, but go and give it to her. רצה לחזור
יחזור *ratza lachzor yachzor*, he can retract. טעמא דאמר אי אפשי *ta'ama
d'amar ee efshi*, it's because he rejected this guy's role as שליח
לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah*. הא לא אמר אי אפשי רצה לחזור לא יחזור
*ha lo amar ee efshi ratza lachzor lo yachzor*. He can't retract.
So, right, the guy presents himself as a שליח לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah*.
If the husband would say הולך *holech*, it's clear from our משנה
*mishna* that that would be binding. So מאי לאו בהיליך ורבי נתן
*mai lav b'heilech v'Rabbi Natan*? It's such a funny proof. Right, all
these cases are הולך *holech* and the גמרא *Gemara* says, oh, he
must be talking about היליך *heilech* and רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan*. But
basically just means since all of this is said סתם *stam* and
there's no debate in any of these ברייתות *braitot*, let's just assume
it's לדברי הכל *l'divrei hakol* because it's a case of היליך *heilech*
and that רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan* would agree with a case of
היליך *heilech*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לא בהולך ורבי *lo b'holech
v'Rebbi*. No, you're right. In our משנה *mishna* it's הולך *holech* and
it works, but that's רבי *Rebbi*. It's not היליך *heilech*. תא שמע
*ta shema*, come and hear. הולך גט זה לאשתי רצה לחזור יחזור
*holech get ze l'ishti ratza lachzor yachzor*. Now finally we have a
ברייתא *braita* that really speaks to the point. If a guy says
הולך *holech* to my wife, he can retract. היליך גט זה לאשתי
רצה לחזור לא יחזור *heilech get ze l'ishti ratza lachzor lo yachzor*.
But if he says היליך *heilech*, he can't retract. So מאן שמעת
ליה דאמר בהולך רצה לחזור יחזור *man sham'at lei d'amar b'holech ratza
lachzor yachzor*? Who's the one that said that הולך *holech* you can
retract even if the guy's a שליח לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah*? רבי נתן
*Rabbi Natan*. וקאמר בהיליך רצה לחזור לא יחזור *v'ka'amar b'heilech ratza lachzor
lo yachzor*. But it says by a case of היליך *heilech*, it
makes this ברייתא *braita* makes a distinction between הולך *holech* and היליך
*heilech*. So that can only be רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan*. שמע מינה
היליך כזכי דמי שמע מינה *shma mina heilech k'zachi dami shma mina*.
Which is fine, which makes sense. Other than that they sound similar,
they're completely different words. Okay, so the question we raised earlier in
the you know, in yesterday's דף *daf*, which we continued a bit
today, whether הולך *holech* is כזכי *k'zachi* is a debate of רבי
*Rebbi* and רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan*. רבי *Rebbi* says הולך *holech* is
כזכי *k'zachi* in a case in a context where the guy's a
שליח לקבלה *shaliach l'kabbalah*. And רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan* says it is
not, but היליך *heilech* everybody would agree is כזכי *k'zachi* because היליך
*heilech* just means "take it". Okay, now finally we switch to a
slightly different topic. אתמר *itmar*. התקבל לי גיטי *hitkabel li giti*. האשה
שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי *ha'isha she'amra hitkabel li giti*. והוא אמר הולך
ותן לה *v'hu amar holech v'ten lah*. Okay, so we're back to
this case where now the here the case is the guy knows
what the שליח *shaliach*'s role is, the שליח *shaliach* is correctly reporting
it, and the husband does not say אי אפשי *ee efshi*, okay,
but he says הולך ותן לה *holech v'ten lah*. So this is
a case basically about הולך *holech*. Okay we're so actually I lied,
it wasn't a different topic. I thought
we were... receive it, accept it, זכי? Or does he mean to
say, no, no, no, I'm not accepting you as a שליח לקבלה
I want you to be a שליח להולכה? And this is the
question, whether הולך is כזכי or not. Okay, so let's read that
again. התקבל גט זה לאשתי ובשליח לקבל לי גיטי, והוא אמר הולך
ותן לה. hitkabel get ze l'ishti u'v'shaliach lekabel li giti, vehu amar
holech veten lah. אמר רבי אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב, amar
Rabbi Abba amar Rav Huna amar Rav, נעשה שלוחו ושלוחה. naaseh shlucho
u'shlucha.
So basically says I don't know. I mean this is a nice
way of saying it. You're both. The שליח is both her שליח
and his שליח. Basically the wife made him a שליח לקבלה, the
husband it sounds like made him a שליח להולכה,
okay, so we don't know which way to interpret it, so we're
sort of stuck. We don't know whether he's the husband's שליח and
she isn't divorced yet, or whether what he's the wife's שליח and
she is divorced yet.
וכל שכן, vechol sheken, if the husband's שליח, are we saying that
even if she gets it?
No, she gets it she'll definitely be divorced ממה נפשך. mima nafshach.
Okay, wait, but before she gets it. So if the wife dies,
if the husband dies before the wife gets it, so is the
wife an אלמנה almanah or is she a גרושה? grusha? And the
נפקא מינה nafka mina besides for a כהן kohein would be if
there's a brother-in-law around, does she have to do חליצה? chalitzah? So
or so he says she has to do חליצה, chalitzah, she can't
do יבום. yibbum. That's a way of demonstrating that it's a ספק,
safek, right? If she was ודאי vadai an אלמנה, almanah, she could
do יבום. yibbum. If she was ודאי vadai a גרושה, grusha, she
wouldn't need to do יבום yibbum either. So חליצה chalitzah means we
don't know if she's a גרושה grusha or an אלמנה. almanah. Okay,
so this is basically, although it sounded like, you know, it was
only רבי נתן who had a problem with הולך, now we're showing
that we ourselves have a doubt whether הולך in this context means
זכי or not and she's a ספק. safek. Okay. למימרא דמספקא ליה
לרב אי הולך כזכי דמי או לאו כזכי דמי? leimra d'misfaka lei
l'Rav ee holech k'zichi dami o lav k'zichi dami? It sounds like
Rav doesn't know the conclusion of our earlier discussion, or like you
know, how to conclude that question. והאיתמר veha'itmar what we taught, הולך
מנה לפלוני שאני חייב לו, holech maneh l'ploni she'ani chayav lo, if
I say to a שליח, here go bring $100 to so-and-so, I
owe him this money, אמר רב חייב באחריותו. amar Rav chayav b'acharayuto.
So since the guy, I say to Michael, bring you know, bring
David the $100 I owe him, so I can't say to David,
hey I already paid off your debt because I gave it to
Michael, because David will say I never made Michael my שליח, you
can't get off of your responsibility that way, so I'm חייב באחריות
chayav b'achrayus until you get the money. But nevertheless ואם בא לחזור
אינו חוזר, v'im ba lachazor eino chozer, I can't say to Michael,
Michael give me that money back, I'm going to pay David some
other time, because Michael automatically has taken enough possession for you on
your behalf, not that the debt is paid up, but that you
now are in possession of it that I can't demand it back.
Let's not get into that too
and then I don't know, I don't want to get into that.
Anyway what you see is, says the גמרא, that sounds like that
although I said הולך, we're interpreting it as זכי, like I'm giving
Michael the right to take possession for you. Okay, so why there
we interpret it like זכי and here we don't know? So the
גמרא says no, התם ספק ממונא לקולא הכא ספק איסורא לחומרא. hatam
safek mamona l'kula hacha safek issura l'chumra. No, we don't know the
הלכה halacha there either. Okay, which now that we say it means
זכי, we just say that it's a ספק, safek, and since it's
a ספק, safek, you know, the person in possession, now Michael's in
possession for David or whatever, then I can't demand, like המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, right? So I can't demand the
money back, but we're not saying it ודאי vadai belongs, David has
rights to it, we're just saying it's a ספק. safek. Here too
we're saying it's a ספק, safek, so it's not that it's any
clearer. Okay. אמר רב, so anyway, so the whole סוגיא ended with
although all the weight was that הולך was כזכי, it ended with
a ספק, safek, and it's not clear right again how would we
פסקן pasken the הלכה? halacha? Do we פסקן pasken the ספק safek
at the end or do we פסקן pasken that it is
כזכי? Okay, so that's anyway the end of that whole discussion of
הולך כזכי, it's a מחלוקת תנאים machlokes tannaim and it ended with
a ספק. safek. Now the גמרא says like this, אמר רב,
אין האשה עושה שליח לקבל גיטה מיד שליח בעלה, ein ha'isha osa
shaliach lekabel gita miyad shaliach ba'alah, ורבי חנינא אמר אשה עושה שליח
לקבל גיטה מיד שליח בעלה. v'Rabbi Chanina amar isha osa shaliach lekabel
gita miyad shaliach ba'alah. So you might remember we had this before.
Okay, I make Michael here as a שליח to give a גט
to my wife. David, now he's my wife, okay.
Can David go ahead, so my שליח can give the גט to
David, but can David go ahead and make a שליח, make Joe
here a שליח to accept the גט from Michael, that neither parties,
right, they're going to be represented by their lawyers, by their agents,
neither party wants to meet with one another. Can that work? So
why not? If you can, if each side can have a שליח,
you know, if you can have one שליח, why can't you have
two שלוחין, shluchin, one שליח for each side? So מאי טעמא דרב,
mai ta'ama d'Rav, why does Rav say you can't have two
שלוחין? shluchin? איבעית אימא משום בזיון דבעל. iba'it eima mishum bizayon d'baal.
Maybe because I the husband, who'm completely in control here and have
all the power, so you know, but so that's exactly why I,
so I don't want my honor, it's so funny, right, here I
am, I'm completely unilaterally dismissing my wife, but I don't want to
feel offended in the process. So what? I'm not good enough for
her to actually come in person? She has to send a שליח?
Of course, she's not, I'm not coming in person either, but okay,
I don't have to come in person. She needs to come in
person, I'm offended. Now if if I was giving it directly to
her שליח I can't say that I was offended because I saw
that it was her שליח and I was still willing to give
it to the שליח. But if I'm not there and I hear
later that she had sent a שליח then I can say had
I known she'd sent a שליח I never would have wanted my
שליח to give it to her. I only wanted my שליח to
give it to herself. Okay so if I'm there in person and
I give it to the שליח it's okay. But if it's my
שליח and I'm not there I could say I would have been
offended if I had known that I wouldn't have wanted that. Okay?
So that's number one. איבעית אימא משום חצר הבאה מאחריה כאן Iba'it
eima mishum chatzer haba'ah me'achareha kan or the other thing is a
different concern. It's that if I go ahead and I put a
גט into into Michael's field and I say I am delivering this
גט and I'm putting it into Michael's field and then my wife
buys the field off of Michael she's not divorced right? Because the
act if it was her field when I put it in she
would be divorced. But if the גט was already in the field
and then she purchased it she's not. So somehow we see that
when she's somehow if she's there and she receives a גט from
Michael we see that as an act of giving the גט. But
if she's not there to or if somehow if I'm there we
see it as an act. But if neither party are there and
somehow the גט goes from Michael's hands to my wife's שליח's hands
or whatever and neither there was no obvious act of giving a
גט neither party was like present that feels too much like this
other case where she buys the where she buys the field that
the גט happens to be in. Okay? So rabbinically we have a
problem with that. Alright? So the so that would be the difference.
So the גמרא says
but I can also say give it to my wife or any
of her שליחין? shluchin? Or can I not do that?
You mean a נפקא מינה nafka mina would be where I'm explicitly
saying that I'm okay with it. Yeah. Right so let's take a
look. The גמרא says מאי בינייהו mai beineihu what's the difference? איכא
בינייהו דשוויה שליח מעיקרא. ika beineihu d'shavyei shaliach me'ikara.
So one נפקא מינה nafka mina would be that my wife made
her שליח before I made mine. So since somehow in that case
when I first give it to my שליח and then the wife
somehow this case of חצר הבאה מאחריה כאן chatzer haba'ah me'achareha kan
is only if her שליח comes in the picture after I gave
it to my my שליח. Then it's like she was like you
know
excuse me excuse me
then it's like somehow
because partly also the idea is we somehow see this case as
I don't really fully get this but we see this case as
if I made Michael the שליח to give the גט right let's
say she turned around and she said you know what Michael just
receive the גט for me right? So that would really be like
a חצר הבאה מאחריה כאן chatzer haba'ah me'achareha kan right? You understand?
Like I put it in Michael's yard and she bought Michael's yard
that doesn't work. I gave Michael the גט to deliver and she
says Michael just accept the גט for me on you know turn
around from being his שליח to my שליח. Okay that would be
a חצר הבאה מאחריה כאן. chatzer haba'ah me'achareha kan. So the similarity
case is is that she makes her שליח after I made Michael's
after I made Michael my שליח. But if she made her שליח
first that's somehow not so comparable to this חצר הבאה מאחריה כאן
chatzer haba'ah me'achareha kan because because דהשתא חצר הבאה מאחריה dehashta chatzer
haba'ah me'achareha is first I put the גט in the yard and
then she takes possession of the yard. So I don't really get
the exact comparison but anyway that would be the difference. תוספות Tosafot
has an easier נפקא מינה. nafka mina. תוספות's Tosafot נפקא מינה nafka
mina is what Michael says. איכא בינייהו דשוויה שליח מעיקרא ika beineihu
d'shavyei shaliach me'ikara תוספות Tosafot says הוה מצי למימר דאיכא בינייהו היכא
דלא קפיד בעל. havah matzi lemeimar d'ika beineihu heicha d'lo kapid ba'al.
The
simple case is the husband explicitly says I'm okay if you give
it to her שליח. Okay? So in that case it can't be
my the fact that I don't want it. But if the rabbis
don't like it because it looks like some case of buying the
husband's field off of the husband when the גט was already given
that would be no good. Another נפקא מינה nafka mina could be
what's the הלכה בדיעבד? halacha b'diavad? Right? If it's really that the
בעל ba'al was מקפיד makpid then בדיעבד b'diavad it might not be
good if we assume the בעל didn't want it. Whereas if it's
a rabbinic concern that it doesn't look good okay then בדיעבד b'diavad
maybe it is good. Alright but anyway that's the question. Let's just
read I know it's already over time but let's just read one
more sentence here. The גמרא says like this. ההוא גברא דשדרה גיטא
לדביתהו hahu gavra d'shadara gita l'deviteihu
a man sent a גט to his wife. אשכחה שליח כי יתבה
וקלישה ashkachah shaliach ki yatva ve-kalisha לישה lisha
he saw that she was sitting and she was kneading dough she
couldn't you know her hands were dirty. אמר לה amar lah so
she said to her to the שליח he said to her היי
לך גיטך heilech giteich here's your גט. אמרה ליה amrah leih she
said back to him ליהוי בידך leihavei beyadeich you know what you
hold onto it you which is exactly the case I gave before.
Turning the husband's שליח להולכה to her שליח לקבלה. Okay? So that
would be a real like חצר הבאה מאחריה chatzer haba'ah me'achareha that's
really like buying the field off of you know once the גט
was put in a field and then buying that field. Once the
גט was already in the hand turning the שליח who has the
גט turning him around to be her שליח. Okay? So אמר רב
נחמן אם איתא לדרבי חנינא amar Rav Nachman im ita l'deRabbi Chanina
if we פסקן pasken like רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina that a woman
a woman's שליח could accept the גט from the husband's שליח. So
עבדינן עובדא avdinan uvda I would have פסקנד pasken'd that that would
have been okay. Okay? Because basically it's she's turned the שליח into
her שליח that would be good according to רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
right? רב doesn't like it but רבי חנינא's Rabbi Chanina okay with
it. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אמר ליה רבא ואם איתא דרבי
חנינא *Amar lei Rava ve-im ita d'Rabbi Chanina*, wait a minute. Even
according to רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* that a woman could make her
שליח *shliach* for the husband's שליח *shliach*, עבדת בה עובדא *Avdas bei
uvda*, you would have פסקן *paskened* that way? הלא הדרה שליחות אצל
הבעל *Ha lo had hazra shlichus eitzel habaal*, but the שליחות *shlichus*
did not return to the husband. So what this means is, and
we'll stop here, we'll pick up with this tomorrow, but what this
means is there's a big difference if my שליח *shliach* gives to
her שליח *shliach* and you have two parties, right? That's one thing.
But to turn my שליח *shliach* into her שליח *shliach*, you could
say, you know, there's no act of giving, that's just like, that
really is like the case of buying the גט *get*, you know,
the field with the גט *get* in it, right? Where does the
שליח *shliach* give the גט *get*? You need two parties, you need
the שליח *shliach* who's giving and the שליח *shliach* who's receiving. If
I just turn him into, so the way the גמרא *Gemara* phrases
it is, the שליח *shliach* can never go back to the husband
and say I finished the job, meaning his identity changed before the
act was complete, right? The שליח *shliach*'s identity has to persist after
the act, he has to still be in his role of representing
the husband after, while, and after he's giving the גט *get*. That
role of representing the husband he can't transform to now representing the
other side before the act of the giving the גט *get* has
been finished.
Okay, the גמרא *Gemara* says it's okay if there's two parties.
If there's two parties. But for one party to switch sides, that's
what the גמרא *Gemara* calls a problem of הדרה שליחות אצל הבעל
*had hazra shlichus eitzel habaal*, that the same guy to do the
act switched his identity, and there was really no act of delivering
the גט *get*. That's a problem, and that's really is similar to
the case of חצר הבאה לאחר מיכן *chatzer haba meacharei mikon*. Okay,
so we will pick up with this fresh issue
tomorrow.